Gerald R. Gill Papers MS170
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Gerald R. Gill Papers
1921 -- 2007
circa 1980s -- 2007
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Gill, Gerald R.
MS170
59.86 Linear Feet 46 record cartons, 2 document boxes, and 2 oversize boxes
575.2 Megabytes
18,443 Digital Object(s) 15,505 email messages with 1,922 attachments; 1,016 born-digital files.
Gerald R. Gill was a professor of American history at Tufts University from 1980 until his death in 2007. His research interests included African-American history, the history of the civil rights movement, pacifism, and the black student experience at Tufts. His papers document his teaching, research, university service, and scholarly activities, and include correspondence, subject files, teaching materials, and writings. There are also biographical materials, audiovisual materials, and photographs.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in ten series: Audiovisual materials and photographs; Biographical materials; Correspondence; Events; Objects; Research and subject files; Teaching materials; University service; Writings; and Digital files.
Custodial History
After Gill's death in 2007, Digital Collections and Archives (DCA) staff packed up his office in East Hall and moved items to the East Hall basement. Lawyers for Ayanna Gill packed up personal materials for return to her at the same time. One of Gill's previous offices had been packed up by the History Department at an unknown point in the past and had also been stored in the East Hall basement. DCA also packed up books and manuscripts in Gill's apartment. Materials now in Box 50, including a manuscript for Dissent, Discontent, and Disinterest: Afro-American Opposition to the United States Wars of the 20th Century and editor's comments were brought to DCA by Susanne Belovari, Archivist for Reference and Collections, in 2007. The remaining materials stayed in the East Hall basement until a deed of gift was signed in September 2016 and the materials were delivered to DCA by Personal Movers on October 18, 2016. Two further accruals, of five and four boxes, were transferred to DCA on November 29, 2016 and December 13, 2016 by Dan Santamaria, University Archivist, and Adrienne Pruitt, Collections Management Archivist.
Scope and Contents
The Gerald R. Gill papers consist primarily of professional papers relating to his career as a professor of American history at Tufts University (1980-2007). His papers include correspondence, research and subject files, teaching materials, records of university service, and writings. The collection also includes biographical materials, audiovisual materials, photographs, and objects. Photographs chiefly document Black student life at Tufts, the bulk apparently sent to Gill by Black alumni. There are also photographs of Gill, often at university events. Audiovisual materials include Black alumni oral histories. Digital files include student papers, teaching materials, event programs and fliers, and university memos.
Research and subject files, teaching materials, and writings reveal Gill's research interests, which focused on African-American history. Topics include the history of protest, the civil rights movement, pacifism, American sports history, Boston race relations, and the experience of Black faculty, staff, and students at Tufts. Teaching materials contain syllabi, class handouts, course readings, exams, assignments, and papers, some of which consist of oral histories conducted by students about the civil rights movement. Gill's university service records detail his work for many Tufts committees and his extensive undergraduate mentoring and advising duties. The bulk of the materials in this collection date from the 1980s-2007, with a small amount of material from the 1950s-1980s.
Biographical / Historical
Gerald R. Gill (1948-2007) taught American history at Tufts University from 1980-2007. He began as an assistant professor, served as an associate professor beginning in 1987, and became the history department's deputy chair in 1998. He was a leading scholar in the field of African-American history and the history of the civil rights movement. He was also a founding and core member of several interdisciplinary programs at Tufts, including American Studies, Africa in the New World Studies, and Peace and Justice Studies.
Gill was born on November 18, 1948 in New Rochelle, New York, to Robert and Etta Gill. He received a bachelor's degree in history in 1970 from Lafayette College, where he was one of the founders of Lafayette's Association of Black Collegians and the Black Cultural Center. He then earned a master's degree in United States history (1974) and a doctorate in history (1985) from Howard University in Washington D.C. A conscientious objector during the Vietnam War, Gill wrote his dissertation on the history of twentieth-century African-American pacifism.
Gill taught at Howard University (1975-1978), University of the District of Columbia (1978), Harvard University (1979), and UCLA (1986), in addition to Tufts University (1980-2007). He received a number of teaching awards and honors, including Professor of the Year for Massachusetts (twice, in 1995 and 1999); the Lerman-Neubauer Prize for Outstanding Teaching and Advising (1998); the Tufts Community Union Senate's Professor of the Year Award (1999); and the Lillian and Joseph Leibner Award for Distinguished Teaching and Advising (1993). The Distinguished Service Award for Outstanding Contributions to the Tufts Community, bestowed on Gill in 2000 by the university's Africana Center, was renamed the Gerald R. Gill Distinguished Service Award in his honor the same year. He was also awarded research fellowships at the W.E.B. Dubois Institute at Harvard (1979), the Center for Afro-American Studies at U.C.L.A. (1985), and a National Endowment for the Humanities fellowship at the Schomberg Center for Research in Black Culture (1997).
Gill's university service included membership on many committees, particularly those related to undergraduate education and advising. In addition to teaching, mentoring students, and writing, Gill served as a consultant on many public television and documentary projects, including Eyes on the Prize, The American Experience, Africans in America, This Far by Faith, and I'll Make Me a World. He was the author of Meanness Mania: The Changed Mood (1980), co-authored The Case for Affirmative Action for Blacks in Higher Education (1978), edited the Faculty Guide and Student Study Guide for the Eyes on the Prize (1991), and co-edited The Eyes on the Prize Civil Rights Reader (1991). At the time of his death, he was working on two unpublished books: Struggling Yet in Freedom's Birthplace: The Civil Rights Movement in Boston, 1935-1972, a history of Boston race relations; and Dissent, Discontent and Disinterest: Afro-American Opposition to the United States War of the Twentieth Century, an extension of his doctoral dissertation.
Gill was divorced with one daughter, Ayanna Gill. He died in Cambridge, Massachusetts, on July 26, 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ayanna Gill, 2016, accession 2017.030.
Separated Materials
58 boxes (69.6 cubic feet) of books, serial publications, and commercially produced VHS tapes, DVDs, and CDs were transferred to Tisch Library.
10 boxes (12 cubic feet) of family and personal belongings, and items with monetary value such as gift cards and historical ephemera and memorabilia, were separated for potential return to the donor.
50 boxes (60 cubic feet)of course reserves, student work, review copies, publications, office supplies, and materials containing personally identifiable information were separated for deaccession or destruction pending donor review.
Related Materials
Africana Center Records, 1969-2012. Tufts University. Digital Collections and Archives. Medford, MA.
Jeanne Penvenne Papers on Gerald Gill, circa 1995-2007. Tufts University. Digital Collections and Archives. Medford, MA.
Conscientious objection; African Americans -- Civil rights; African Americans -- History; Tufts University -- History; Protest movements; Oral history; Political activists; Faculty papers; African American history
- Audiovisual materials and photographs, circa 1974 -- 2008; MS170.001; 1.5 Linear Feet 1 full and 1 partial record carton
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series is open for research.
  Arrangement
  Photographs are arranged by date and audiovisual materials by title. This series had no received order and order has been imposed by the processing archivists.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains audiovisual materials and photographs. Formats include photographic prints, slides, negatives, a film strip, VHS tapes, CDs, audiocassettes, and 45 rpm and 33 1/3 rpm records. The audiovisual materials contain a small body of material (two VHS tapes and an audiocassette) that appear to relate to the "Another Light on the Hill" exhibit research. There are nine audiocassettes and related documentation from the Victoria Norman "Black at Tufts" project, which appear to contain oral histories and may also relate to the exhibit.
  The audiovisual materials also include teaching materials and student projects. There are a number of mix tapes and two audiocassettes with no label; they have not been reviewed and their contents are unknown.
  Photographs primarily document Black student life at Tufts in the 1980s-1990s. Correspondence suggests that these photographs were donated by Black alumni in an effort to document their time on campus as a part of the "Another Light on the Hill" exhibit. Other materials include photos of Gill at campus events and Gill's professional headshots. Additionally, there are small art prints and a signed photo of Lenny Kravitz.
  - A.A. MacNeil, "An Artistic Expression of Gullah on St. Helena," audiocassette, circa 1990; MS170.001.002.00019; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
    Open for research.
  - Alphonzo "Phonzileo" Terrell, CD, 2000; MS170.001.002.00026; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
  - "Another Light on the Hill" African American Students at Tufts, 1900 to Present, VHS, circa 1999; MS170.001.002.00001; 1 Video Recordings (Box 2)
  - "Another Light on the Hill" African American Students at Tufts, 1900 to Present, VHS, circa 1999; MS170.001.002.00002; 1 Video Recordings (Box 2)
  - "Blue Oranges, a Small Dog…Silent Anticipations Mix," audiocassette, circa 1990; MS170.001.002.00030; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
  - Buffalo Soldier Mutiny DVD with documentation, 2008; MS170.001.001.00025; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Dr. Soi-Daniel W. Brown, "The Dreamer is Gone," audiocassette, circa 1990; MS170.001.002.00008; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
  - Edward "Ted" Dwyer, "The Door of No Return," CDs, circa 2000; MS170.001.002.00015; 2 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
  - Elizabeth Lee Mochizuki, appendix for American Studies Honors Thesis "The Asian American Experience in Ballet," VHS, 2003; MS170.001.002.00012; 1 Video Recordings (Box 2)
  - Eric Befeler, "Can't Be Trusted Blues: Blues in the South," audiocassette, circa 1990; MS170.001.002.00031; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
  - Excerpts, 1960s at Tufts, audiocassette, circa 1990; MS170.001.002.00003; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
  - "Freedom Freeform," audiocassette, 1990-04-04; MS170.001.002.00028; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
  - The Great Depression teaser, VHS, circa 1990; MS170.001.002.00011; 1 Video Recordings (Box 2)
  - Greg Kallor, senior recital, CD, 2000; MS170.001.002.00013; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
  - Insurgent 33.3 and 45 rpm records, 2000 -- 2001; MS170.001.001.00023; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Interview with Marily Glater, audiocassette, circa 1990; MS170.001.002.00017; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
  - Malcolm X, "Ballot or the Bullet," audiocassette, 1964-04-12; MS170.001.002.00007; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
  - Malcolm X, "Last Message," Detroit, audiocassette, 1965-02-14; MS170.001.002.00004; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
  - Malcolm X, "Prospects for Freedom," New York City, audiocassette, 1965-01-07; MS170.001.002.00006; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
  - Mellow Breakbeats, CD, circa 2000; MS170.001.002.00025; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
  - Minister L. Farrakhan, "Trial and Orgena in Boston," parts 1-4, audiocassettes, 1963; MS170.001.002.00005; 2 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
  - "Music for the Soul," audiocassette, circa 1990; MS170.001.002.00029; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
  - Professor Betty Rothenberg, audiocassette, circa 1990; MS170.001.002.00018; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
  - Sam Lawrence, "Affirmative Action: A Road to Better Cultural Exchange?" VHS, circa 2002; MS170.001.002.00010; 1 Video Recordings (Box 2)
  - Sandi McLendon, "Towards a Just World," audiocassette, circa 1990; MS170.001.002.00027; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
  - Sandra Hanna, women's studies project, audiocassette, circa 1990; MS170.001.002.00020; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
  - The Sculpture of Africa, film strip, 1970; MS170.001.002.00009; 1 Audiovisual Object(s) (Box 2)
  - Sirens extra, CD, circa 2000; MS170.001.002.00014; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
  - Theda [Sandiford?], "Will the Real Black People Please Stand Up?" audiocassette, 1990; MS170.001.002.00021; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
  - Theda Sandiford, Lahill Humefront, "Black an' 'Blue' Poetry: World War II Blues," audiocassette, 1991; MS170.001.002.00022; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
  - "To a Professor," audiocassette, circa 1990; MS170.001.002.00016; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
  - Unlabeled audiocassettes, circa 1990; MS170.001.002.00032; 2 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
  - Victoria Norman, "Blacks at Tufts," special project, transcripts and documentation, 1985 -- 1986; MS170.001.002.00023; 1 Folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Victoria Norman, "Blacks at Tufts," special project, audiocassettes, circa 1983 -- 1986; MS170.001.002.00024; 9 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
    - Blank audiocassette, circa 1983 -- 1986; MS170.001.002.00024.00001; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
    - Sandra Greer and Clifton Graves, circa 1983 -- 1986; MS170.001.002.00024.00002; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
    - Henry Owens, attorney, Local President of the NAACP, 1983-09-19; MS170.001.002.00024.00003; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
    - Arthur Williams, circa 1983 -- 1986; MS170.001.002.00024.00004; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
    - Cortlisse Thomas, circa 1983 -- 1986; MS170.001.002.00024.00005; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
    - Clifton Graves, circa 1983 -- 1986; MS170.001.002.00024.00006; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
    - Arthur Williams and Robert Kelley, circa 1983 -- 1986; MS170.001.002.00024.00007; 1 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
    - Charles Yancey, circa 1983 -- 1986; MS170.001.002.00024.00008; 2 Sound Recordings (Box 2)
  - Photographs of Black students at Tufts, 1972; MS170.001.001.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Black students at Tufts, 1974 -- 1980; MS170.001.001.00002; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Unidentified photographs, 1977 -- 1987; MS170.001.001.00003; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Black students at Tufts, 1977 -- 1983; MS170.001.001.00004; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of Black students at Tufts, 1978 -- 1986; MS170.001.001.00005; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Black students at Tufts with information about majors, 1979; MS170.001.001.00006; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photograph of the Tufts men's basketball team, 1980; MS170.001.001.00007; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photographs of Black Tufts students and alumni, 1980 -- 1987; MS170.001.001.00008; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Photographs of Tufts students' parties, 1982 -- 1983; MS170.001.001.00009; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photographs and correspondence from Troy Cooper, 1982 -- 1989; MS170.001.001.00010; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Unidentified photographs, 1985; MS170.001.001.00011; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Signed photograph of Lenny Kravitz, circa 1990; MS170.001.001.00012; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Art photographs and photographs of murals, 1991; MS170.001.001.00013; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Photograph of Gerald Gill for the H and A newsletter with correspondence, 1995 -- 1999; MS170.001.001.00014; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Unidentified photographs with Gerald Gill, 1997 -- 2000; MS170.001.001.00015; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "Another Light on the Hill" slides and negatives, circa 1999; MS170.001.001.00016; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Photographs of the USS Arizona Memorial and USS Missouri, 1999; MS170.001.001.00017; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Photographs of a student award ceremony at Tufts, 1999; MS170.001.001.00018; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Photographs of Tufts events, 1999; MS170.001.001.00019; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Negatives from seniors' reception at Tufts, 1999; MS170.001.001.00020; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Copies of Melville Munro photographs, 1999 -- 2003; MS170.001.001.00021; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Headshots of Gerald Gill, 2000; MS170.001.001.00022; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Photograph of Gerald Gill with students and faculty at graduation, 2005; MS170.001.001.00024; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Biographical materials, 1963, 1995 -- 2006; MS170.002; .5 Linear Feet 1 document box
  Biographical materials include curricula vitae, awards and certificates of appreciation, correspondence, an appointment book, a New Rochelle High School class schedule, and an interview with Gill in Long Term View journal titled "Vietnam's Political Legacy for African-Americans." These materials provide an introduction to Gill's academic career, scholastic achievements, and professional life.
  This series is arranged alphabetically by subject, then chronologically.
  - Curriculum vitae, circa 1998; MS170.002.003.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Curriculum vitae, circa 2000; MS170.002.003.00002; 2 Folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
  - Curriculum vitae, circa 2002; MS170.002.003.00003; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Curriculum vitae, circa 2003; MS170.002.003.00005; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Teaching awards correspondence, 1992 -- 1998; MS170.002.003.00006; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - City of Cambridge resolution on selection as 1995 Massachusetts Professor of the Year, MS170.002.003.00007; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Newsletter on Massachusetts Professor of the Year Award, 1995; MS170.002.003.00008; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The Boston and Vicinity Club person of distinction awardee, 1996; MS170.002.003.00009; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Massachusetts Professor of the Year correspondence, 1999; MS170.002.003.00010; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Black Issues in Higher Education article on 1999 Massachusetts Professor of the Year, 2000; MS170.002.003.00011; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Gerald R. Gill Distinguished Service Award application form, 2000; MS170.002.003.00012; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Certificates of appreciation, 2000; MS170.002.003.00013; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Robert Foster Cherry Award correspondence, 2002; MS170.002.003.00014; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous award, circa 1980 -- 2007; MS170.002.003.00015; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - The Long Term View Journal interview, 2000; MS170.002.003.00016; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Appointment book, 2006; MS170.002.003.00017; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Personal statement and letter of recommendation for Gill, 1995; MS170.002.003.00018; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - New Rochelle High School class schedule, 1963; MS170.002.003.00019; 1 Folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Correspondence, circa 1981 -- 2007; MS170.003; 8.4 Linear Feet 7 record cartons; 266 Megabytes; 17,427 Digital Object(s)
  This series contains correspondence sent or received by Gill. Enclosures and attachments to correspondence include artwork, brochures, CDs, fliers, forms, invitations, photographs, and writings. The majority of correspondents are Tufts University colleagues, administrators, students, and alumni. The materials in this series reflect Gill's professional activities and personal relationships.
  Significant topics include Gill's involvement in Tufts Black Alumni events, his work on various projects (including Alaska Highway and Howard Thurman, In Search of Common Ground), and his membership or association with various national organizations, such as the Golden Key National Honor Society. Current and former students often wrote to Gill, and their correspondence reflects his deep commitment to students and the Tufts community. Correspondence from colleagues and administrators touches on his university service in initiatives like the Tufts Black Caucus. The series also includes invitations to participate in various events, such as seminars held at the John F. Kennedy Presidential Library and Museum in Boston. There is some overlap in subject materials between this series, the Events series, and the University service series.
  This series is arranged in two sub-series, Paper mail and Email. Order has largely been imposed by the processing archivists.
  This series contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list.
  Some paper correspondence is unopened. Please consult an archivist regarding access to unopened materials.
  Email will be made available to researchers in the DCA Reading Room. Please contact DCA for further details.
  - Paper mail, circa 1981 -- 2007; MS170.003.001; 8.4 Linear Feet 7 record cartons.
    This sub-series is arranged chronologically, excluding folders 24-29 of Box 8 and folder 6 of Box 10 (the materials in these folders are undated and have been assigned a circa date of 1980 -- 2007).
    Materials in boxes 9 and 10 were originally received in boxes that only contained correspondence (the bulk of Professor Gill's correspondence was originally scattered throughout many boxes and had to be brought together to create this series). The processing archivist kept these materials in boxes 9 and 10 physically together to reflect their received state.
    Because this series possessed no original order, order has been imposed by the processing archivist.
    - Correspondence, 1981 -- 1984, undated; MS170.003.004.00001; 2 Folder(s) (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    - Correspondence, 1981 -- 1984, undated; MS170.003.004.00002; 1 Folder(s) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1983 -- 1990, undated; MS170.003.004.00003; 2 Folder(s) (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
    - Correspondence, 1987; MS170.003.004.00004; 1 Folder(s) (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1987; MS170.003.004.00005; 1 Folder(s) (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1987, undated; MS170.003.004.00006; 1 Folder(s) (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1987 -- 1995, undated; MS170.003.004.00007; 2 Folder(s) (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
    - Correspondence, 1987 -- 2000, undated; MS170.003.004.00008; 1 Folder(s) (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1988 -- 2005, undated; MS170.003.004.00009; 1 Folder(s) (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1989 -- 2006, undated; MS170.003.004.00010; 1 Folder(s) (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, 1990 -- 1991; MS170.003.004.00011; 1 Folder(s) (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 1990 -- 1999; MS170.003.009.00001; 4 Folder(s) (Box 9, Folder 1-4)
    - Correspondence and enclosures, 1990 -- 2006, undated; MS170.003.004.00012; 1 Folder(s) (Box 4, Folder 15)
      75 years from date of creation.
    - Correspondence, 1991 -- 1998, undated; MS170.003.004.00013; 1 Folder(s) (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, 1991 -- 1998, undated; MS170.003.004.00014; 1 Folder(s) (Box 4, Folder 17)